Guide to the Hanover Royal Music Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Duke of Cumberland's Band Archive, circa 1765-1834; Series III; 9; (107 boxes)
  - Weigl, Joseph, 1766-1846
    - [L'uniforme. Overture]. The Celebrated Overture to the Opera of the Uniform…. Arranged by John Collier. Parts (2 fl, 6 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt, trbn). Print (London: W. Milhouse), undated (Box 280, Folder 1495-1496)
      Original folder: numbered 13 and 79
  - Weilland
    - [Harmony]. Harmonie…. Parts (2 ob, 2 cl, 2 bn, 2 hn). Print (Paris: Pleyel), undated; Two copies of 2nd bassoon part (Box 280, Folder 1497-1498)
      Original folder: numbered 22
    - Partita. Parts (2 ob, 2 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn). Manuscript, undated (Box 280, Folder 1499)
      Original folder: not present; music numbered 3
  - Weyse, Christoph Ernst Friedrich, 1774-1842
    - [Symphony]. Arranged by Henry Pick. Parts (2 fl, 2 ob, 5 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, 2 tpt, trbn, timp). Manuscript, undated (Box 280, Folder 1500-1502)
      Original folder: numbered 14 and 104
  - Winter, Peter von, 1754-1825
    - Douze Nouvelles Suites d'harmonie…Suivies de Marches et pas Redoublés par J. Gebauer…Suite 111…4e. Livraison…. Le Sacrifice interompu. Parts (2 fl, 2 ob, 2 cl, 3 bn, 3 hn, tpt). Print (Paris: Sieber père), undated (Box 281, Folder 1503-1505)
      Original folder: numbered 65
    - [La grotta di Calipso. Excerpt]. Duetto in the Opera of Calipso. Parts (2 fl, 4 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn). Manuscript, undated (Box 281, Folder 1506-1507)
      Original folder: numbered 2 and 221
      On versos: Duetto by W. A. Mozart. Parts (2 fl, 4 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn). Manuscript.
      With: Pieces d'harmonie. Parts (2 cl, 2 bn, 2 hn). Print. No publisher information.
    - [Das Labyrinth. Overture]. Parts (2 fl, 2 ob, 4 cl, 2 bn, spt, 4 hn, 2 tpt, trbn, timp). Manuscript, undated (Box 281, Folder 1508)
      Original folder: not present; music numbered 29
    - [Das Labyrinth. Excerpts]. Arranged by Keil. Parts (2 ob, 2 cl, 2 bn, 2 hn). Manuscript, undated (Box 282-283, Folder 1509-1513)
      Original folder: numbered 3 and 218
    - [Il ratto di Proserpina. Excerpt]. Duetto. Arranged Frederick Eley. Parts (2 fl, 4 cl, 2 bn (1 part), spt, 2 hn, tpt). Manuscript, undated (Box 283, Folder 1514-1515)
      Original folder: numbered 7 and 219
    - A Set of Military Pieces…. Parts (2 fl, 4 cl, 2 bn (1 part), spt, 2 hn, tpt). Print (no publisher information), undated (Box 284, Folder 1516-1517)
      Original folder: numbered 54
    - A 2nd Set of Four Military Marches & Divertimentos…Composed Expressly for M Kelly By Mr. Winter. Parts (fl, 2 cl, 2 bn, 2 hn, tpt, b). Print (London: M. Kelly), undated (Box 284, Folder 1518-1519)
      Original folder: numbered 55
    - [Sinfonie concertante]. Parts (2 fl, 8 cl, 3 bn, 2 spt, 3 hn, 2 tpt, 3 trbn). Manuscript, undated (Box 284, Folder 1520-1521)
    - [Das unterbrochene Opferfest. Excerpts]. Opera das Opferfest. Arranged by Keil. Parts (2 ob, 2 cl, 2 bn, 2 hn). Manuscript, undated (Box 285-286, Folder 1522-1526)
      Original folder: numbered 4 and 217
    - [Zaire. Excerpts]. No.1. Sommo Dio che in sen mi vedi. No. 2. O Giove onnipotente. Arranged Frederick Eley. Parts (2 fl, 2 cl, 2 bn, spt, 3 hn). Manuscript, undated (Box 286, Folder 1527-1528)
      Original folder: numbered 1 and 253
  - Wranitzky, Paul, 1756-1808
    - [Symphony, op. 2, C major]. Parts (2 vn, 2 va, vc and b (1 part), 2 fl, 2 ob, 2 bn, 2 hn, 2 tpt, timp). Manuscript, undated (Box 286-287, Folder 1529-1531)
  - Zwingmann, John N.
    - Fifteen Military Divertisements….Op.2. Parts (2 fl, 2 cl, 2 bn, 2 hn, tpt). Print (London: printed by the author), undated (Box 287, Folder 1532-1533)
      Original folder: numbered 41
  - Unidentified
    - H.R.H. the Duke of Cumberland's Pas Redouble. No. 4. Parts (fl, 2 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt, trbn, bass drum and cymbal (1 part)). Print (no publisher information), undated (Box 287, Folder 1534)
    - H.R.H. the Duke of Cumberland's Pas Redouble. No.6. Parts (fl, 3 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt, trbn, bass drum and cymbal (1 part)). Print (no publisher information), undated (Box 287, Folder 1535)
    - H.R.H. the Duke of Cumberland's Pas Redouble. No.7. Parts (fl, 3 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt, trbn, bass drum and cymbal (1 part)). Print (no publisher information), undated (Box 288, Folder 1536)
    - H.R.H. the Duke of Cumberland's Slow March. No.11. Parts (fl, 3 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt, trbn, bass drum and cymbal (1 part)). Print (no publisher information), undated (Box 288, Folder 1537-1538)
    - Her Royal Highness the Duchess of Cumberlands Collection of Songs. Parts (2 fl, 2 ob, 5 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt, trbn). Manuscript, undated (Box 288, Folder 1539-1542)
      Original folder: numbered 19 and 305
      Collection of music, including music by Josephine Mainvielle-Fodor, Jean-Jacques Rousseau, and Carl Maria von Weber
    - Marcia maestoso. Parts (fl, 2 ob, 2 cl, bn, 2 hn, 2 tpt, cymbals and drum (1 part), triangle). Manuscript, undated (Box 289, Folder 1543-1544)
      Original folder: numbered 60 and 272
    - Military Music. Parts (2 fl, 4 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt). Manuscript, undated (Box 289, Folder 1545-1546)
      Original folder: numbered 62 and 204
    - A 2nd Set of Quartett Books, undated (Box 289, Folder 1547)
      Original folder: numbered 2 and 32
    - A set of books. Parts (2 fl, 2 ob, 2 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt, trbn). Manuscript, undated (Box 289-290, Folder 1548-1552)
      Original folder: numbered 64 and 302
      Collection of music, including William Reeve, Oscar and Malvina overture
    - A Set of Military music. Parts (2 fl, 2 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, tpt). Manuscript, undated (Box 290, Folder 1553-1554)
      Original folder: numbered 33
    - A Sett of Militaire music. Parts (2 fl, 4 cl, 2 bn, spt, 4 hn, tpt). Manuscript, undated (Box 291, Folder 1555-1556)
    - [Waltzes]. Parts (2 fl, 2 ob, 2 cl, 2 bn, spt, 2 hn, 2 tpt, trbn). Manuscript, undated (Box 291, Folder 1557)
      Two waltzes ascribed to Mozart
    - Other unidentified. Various parts and folders. Print and manuscript., undated (Box 291, Folder 1558-1560)
      Original folders: not numbered
  - Other Papers
    - Catalogue of Music for H. R. H. The Duke of Cumberland's Private Band. Manuscript, circa 1830 (Box 876)
      Also used as an account book, 1838-1840
- Hanover Liturgical Manuscripts, 1859-1867; Series IV; 3.83; (46 boxes)
  Series IV, Hanover Liturgical Manuscripts, is organized in five subseries: Liturgical Year, Other Liturgy, Other Choral Music, Copyists' Manuscripts, and Other Music.
  Contents consists of drafts, fair copies, and sets of scores and parts for music apparently performed by the Hanover Hof- and Kirchenchor, 1850s-1860s. Most music is represented by sets of choral parts, usually SSAATTBB, many signed by the singers who used them. Music may have been composed by Arnold Wehner, who served as choir director or Hofkapellmeister during this period. Other manuscript music composed by Wehner is present in the Copyists' Manuscripts subseries and in the General Music and Books About Music series. The General Music and Books About Music series also contains printed sacred music bearing stamps of the Hanover Hof- and Kirchenchor.
  Music for the liturgical year is arranged chronologically by festival day. Other liturgical music is arranged alphabetically by type of service, such as royal confirmations or birthdays. Other choral music for unspecified services is arranged by title. Copyists' manuscripts consist of scores and parts for works of identified composers, copied for use in performance. Individual works arranged alphabetically by composer are followed by several sets and collections of music. Many composers present here are also found in the General Music and Books About Music series. Other music consists of unidentified sketches, notes, and unidentified original folders.
  - Liturgical Year
    Arranged chronologically by festival
    - [Advent], drafts and scores, 1859-1860, undated (Box 292, Folder 1561)
    - [Advent, Weihnachten, Busstag, Neujahrstag], parts, undated (Box 292, Folder 1562-1563)
    - [Weihnachten (Christmas)], drafts and scores, 1859, undated (Box 292, Folder 1564)
    - [Silvester], drafts and scores, 1858-1861, undated (Box 292, Folder 1565)
    - [Neujahrstag (New Year)], drafts and scores, undated (Box 292, Folder 1566)
    - [Neujahrstag, Epiphanias], parts, undated (Box 292, Folder 1567)
    - [Epiphanias (Epiphany)], drafts and scores, undated (Box 293, Folder 1568)
    - [Epiphanias, Darstellung Jesu, Septuagesimae], parts, undated (Box 293, Folder 1569-1570)
    - [Septuagesimae (Septuagesima), Sexagesimae (Sexagesima)], score, undated (Box 293, Folder 1571)
    - [Septuagesimae, Sexagesimae, Quinquagesimae, Fastenzeit, Mariae Verkündigung], drafts, scores, and parts, undated (Box 293, Folder 1572)
    - [Fastenzeit (Lent)], drafts, scores, and parts, undated (Box 294, Folder 1573-1574)
    - [Fastenzeit, Mariae Verkündigung, Gründonnerstag], parts, undated (Box 294, Folder 1575-1576)
    - [Aschermittwoch (Ash Wednesday)], parts, undated (Box 294-295, Folder 1577-1579)
    - [Gründonnerstag (Maundy Thursday), Karfreitag], parts, undated (Box 295, Folder 1580-1581)
    - [Gründonnerstag, Karfreitag, Ostern, Christi Himmelfahrt, Pfingsten, Johannes der Täufer, Heimsuchung Mariae], score, undated (Box 296, Folder 1582)
    - [Karfreitag (Good Friday)], drafts, scores, and parts, undated (Box 296, Folder 1583)
    - [Karfreitag]. Improperien, draft and parts, undated (Box 296, Folder 1584-1586)
    - [Karfreitag, Ostern, Freudenzeit, Christi Himmelfahrt, Pfingsten], parts, undated (Box 297, Folder 1587)
    - [Ostern (Easter)], drafts, scores, parts, printed order of service, 1859, 1867, undated (Box 297, Folder 1588)
    - [Ostern, Christi Himmelfahrt], parts, undated (Box 297, Folder 1589-1590)
    - [Pfingsten (Pentecost), Trinitas, Christi Himmelfahrt], drafts, scores, parts, and printed order of service, 1859, 1867, undated (Box 298-299, Folder 1591-1595)
    - [Pfingsten, Trinitas, Johannes der Täufer, Heimsuchung Mariae], parts, undated (Box 299, Folder 1596-1597)
    - [Christi Himmelfahrt (Ascension)], draft, scores, 1859, undated (Box 300, Folder 1598)
    - [Johannes der Täufer, Heimsuchung Mariae, Trinitas], score, undated (Box 300, Folder 1599)
    - [Trinitas (Holy Trinity)], drafts, scores, part, and printed order of service, 1859-1861, undated (Box 300, Folder 1600)
    - [Trinitas, Michaelisfest, Reformationsfest], parts, undated (Box 300-301, Folder 1601-1605)
  - Other Liturgy
    Arranged alphabetically by type of service
    - [Busstag (atonement)], drafts, scores, parts, and printed order of service, 1859-1860, undated (Box 302, Folder 1606-1607)
    - [Christkirche], Grundsteinlegung, draft, score, parts, undated (Box 302, Folder 1608)
    - [Christkirche], Einweihung, score, parts, 1864 (Box 303, Folder 1609-1611)
    - [Confirmation], drafts, undated (Box 303, Folder 1612)
    - [Confirmation], Princess Friederike, Princess Marie, parts, undated (Box 303, Folder 1613)
    - [Confirmation], Ernst August (1845-1923), parts, undated (Box 303, Folder 1614)
    - [Geburtsfest (birthday)], Georg V, drafts, scores, parts, 1861, undated (Box 304-306, Folder 1615-1623)
    - [Geburtsfest], Georg V, Queen Marie, draft, score, parts, 1859, undated (Box 306-308, Folder 1624-1631)
    - [Geburtsfest], Queen Marie, drafts, parts, 1860, undated (Box 308, Folder 1632-1635)
    - [Geburtsfest], Ernst August (1845-1923), draft, scores, 1860, undated (Box 309, Folder 1636)
    - [Geburtsfest], Ernst August (1845-1923), Princess Friederike, Princess Marie, parts, undated (Box 309, Folder 1637-1639)
    - [Geburtsfest], Princess Marie, drafts, undated (Box 309, Folder 1640)
    - [Gustav Adolph Vereins], draft, parts, undated (Box 310, Folder 1641-1642)
    - [Henriettenstiflung], Grundsteinlegung, parts, undated (Box 310, Folder 1643-1645)
    - [Henriettenstiflung], Einweihung, draft, score, parts, 1863 (Box 311, Folder 1646)
    - [Henriettenstiflung], Jahresfeier, parts, 1862 (Box 311, Folder 1647)
    - [Schlosscapelle, Celle], Einweihung, parts, 1866 (Box 311, Folder 1648)
    - [Synode], Eröffnung, drafts, parts, 1863-1864, undated (Box 311, Folder 1649)
    - [Todtenfest], parts, undated (Box 312, Folder 1650)
    - Unidentified, scores, parts, undated (Box 312, Folder 1651-1653)
  - Other Choral Music
    Arranged alphabetically by title
    - "Bitte an den Frühling; Liebe und Frühling," parts, undated (Box 313, Folder 1654-1655)
    - "Gott des Himmels und der Erden; Herr Jesu Christ mein's Lebens Licht," parts, undated (Box 313-314, Folder 1656-1658)
    - "Der Herr ist mein Hirt," score, 1861 Oct 30 (Box 314, Folder 1659-1660)
    - "Du Hirte Israels," parts, undated (Box 314, Folder 1661)
    - "Hymne" (Lasst hell die schönste herrlichste der Weisen ertönen...), score and parts, undated (Box 315, Folder 1662)
    - "Ihr Sternlein dort in der Höhe," parts, undated (Box 315, Folder 1663-1665)
    - "Jesu, meine Freude," parts, undated (Box 315, Folder 1666)
    - "Judas Maccabäus" parts, undated (Box 316, Folder 1667-1668)
    - "Largo" (Et incarnatus est), parts, undated (Box 316, Folder 1669)
    - "Macht hoch die Thur," drafts and parts, undated (Box 316, Folder 1670)
    - "Trauungslied," parts, undated (Box 317, Folder 1671)
    - "Vom Himmel hoch," parts, undated (Box 317, Folder 1672-1673)
    - "Wohl den Frommen...," parts, undated (Box 317, Folder 1674)
    - Unidentified, scores, parts, undated (Box 317-318, Folder 1675-1676)
  - Copyists' Manuscripts
    - Composers (A-B), undated (Box 318, Folder 1677)
    - Composers (Bach, Johann Sebastian, 1685-1750), undated (Box 318, Folder 1678-1680)
    - Composers (Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827), undated (Box 319, Folder 1681)
    - Composers (C-D), undated (Box 319, Folder 1682)
    - Composers (E-G), undated (Box 319, Folder 1683)
    - Composers (Gantzert, B.), undated (Box 319-320, Folder 1684-1685)
    - Composers (Georg V), undated (Box 320, Folder 1686-1688)
    - Composers (Grell, Eduard August, 1800-1886), undated (Box 321, Folder 1689-1693)
    - Composers (H), undated (Box 322, Folder 1694)
    - Composers (Hammerschmidt, Andreas, 1611 or 12-1675), undated (Box 322, Folder 1695-1696)
    - Composers (J-L), undated (Box 322, Folder 1697)
    - Composers (Lotti, Antonio, d. 1740), undated (Box 323-324, Folder 1698-1704)
    - Composers (M), undated (Box 324, Folder 1705)
    - Composers (Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847), undated (Box 324, Folder 1706-1707)
    - Composers (N-P), undated (Box 325, Folder 1708)
    - Composers (Palestrina, Giovanni Pierluigi da, 1525?-1594), undated (Box 325, Folder 1709-1712)
    - Composers (Praetorius, Michael, 1571-1621), undated (Box 326, Folder 1713-1716)
    - Composers (R-S), undated (Box 326, Folder 1717)
    - Composers (Schumann, Robert, 1810-1856), undated (Box 327, Folder 1718)
    - Composers (Schütz, Heinrich, 1585-1672), undated (Box 327-328, Folder 1719-1725)
    - Composers (Spohr, Louis, 1784-1859), undated (Box 329, Folder 1726-1727)
    - Composers (T-W), undated (Box 329, Folder 1728)
    - Composers (Wehner, Arnold), undated (Box 329-332, Folder 1729-1740)
    - "I. Liturgische Gesänge für den Hauptgottesdienst", undated (Box 333, Folder 1741-1744)
    - "II. Allgemeine kirchliche Gesänge", undated (Box 334, Folder 1745-1748)
    - "III. Fest-Gesänge. B. Feiertage", undated (Box 335, Folder 1749-1752)
    - "V. Gesänge für besonder kirchliche Handlungen", undated (Box 336, Folder 1753-1754)
    - Other collections, undated (Box 336, Folder 1755)
  - Other Music
    - Sketches and notes, undated (Box 336-337, Folder 1756-1758)
    - Exercises for chorus, parts, undated (Box 337, Folder 1759)
    - Empty chorus folders, undated (Box 337, Folder 1760)
- Notes of Former Owners, [1980s?]-2005; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series V, Notes of Former Owners, is organized in two subseries: Sotheby's Description and Unidentified Notes.
  Sotheby's Description consists of a collection-level description and a partial list of contents provided by Sotheby's prior to purchase by the Beinecke Library. Unidentified Notes contains notecards and envelopes with notes in German, written in an unidentified hand, which have been removed from individual items in the collection and organized alphabetically by composer or title. Notes generally consist of bibliographic description of individual items, and in some cases include lists of contents or comments on physical condition. Some envelopes were repurposed, and bear unrelated postmarks dating from the 1980s. Additional similar notes were written directly on some items. See Processing Notes for more information.
  - Sotheby's Description
    - Collection-level description, [2005?] (Box 338, Folder 1761)
    - Partial list of contents, 2005 December (Box 338, Folder 1762)
  - Unidentified Notes
    - Names and titles, A-Z, and unidentified, [1980s?] (Box 338, Folder 1763-1771)
    - Music collections, [1980s?] (Box 338, Folder 1772)
    - Hanover liturgical manuscripts, [1980s?] (Box 338, Folder 1773)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.25; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 338, folders 1763-1771, [1980s?] (Box 339, Folder 1774-1782)
  - Box 338, folder 1772, [1980s?] (Box 339, Folder 1783)